A Guide to the Papers of Mark Twain, 1862-1946
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series II: Letters
  - Will [Mantz], San Jose, CA, to Brother [ Samuel E. Moffett], 1898 January 4; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks him for Mark Twain's latest books and glad to see picture of Moffett and Twain; discusses attempts to rent or sell Moffett's Berkeley real estate; encloses check for Moffett's mother and best wishes for New Year; mentions family news.
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Vienna, to Frank Marshall White, 1898 January 6; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks him on behalf of Mark Twain for the note; Twain was sorry that White's request for article on "the Reichrath's affair" came too late.] (mourning stationery)
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Vienna, to Frank Marshall White, 1898 January 11; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Mark Twain requests a confidential cable be sent to Samuel E. Moffett; says cabling from Vienna more expensive than from London; requests price of cable.] (mourning paper)
  - Olivia L. Clemens, Vienna, to Samuel E. Moffett, New York, 1898 January 14; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks him for review of Mark Twain's book ( Following the Equator ); is doing most of Twain's correspondence because Twain is busy working on writing projects; sends regards to family.] (w/env)
  - Annie Moffett Webster, Fredonia, NY, to [ Samuel E. Moffett], 1898 January 22; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Quotes letter she has received from Joseph L. Sheridan answering her request for names of lawyers; lawyer says she can receive the appraised value of the estate from the Hazelwood County clerk; asks him if she should write or would he rather do so.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Frank Marshall White, 1898 February 4; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Requests him not to print the "Comedy" because it would hurt the copyright in England and America; comments on hard work of editing it. M.T.
  - Annie Moffett Webster, Fredonia, NY, to Samuel E. Moffett, 1898 February 5; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Encloses a package of manuscripts for her brother to read and return at least part of them; asked "Syd" to write one of the lawyers; thinks unless he can get better terms they had better sign this contract.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Chatto & Windus, 1898 February 8; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Bemoans fact that Chatto & Windus declined his proposed Dreyfus book; had not occurred to him that he could have the translating and researching done by Harper & Brothers ' house in London. S.L.C.
  - A. Howard Ritter, Philadelphia, to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 February 25; TLS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    The Public Ledger of Philadelphia never received anything on Charles L. Webster & Company account but 2 checks totalling $12.90; asks for when and to whom checks were sent.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Chatto & Windus, 1898 February 26; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses corrections to be made to the "Afrikander paragraph" in Following the Equator and ways of keeping the paragraph in the book; requests copies of A Tramp Abroad; suggests Bliss make postcards, not calendar, of maxims from The Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson; asks if Chatto & Windus may want to do this as well. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1898 March 12; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Mentions great appreciation for MacAlister saying in the Times that Twain has worked himself out of debt; thanks him for all his past kindnesses in his time of trouble; mentions that he has regained his self-respect and is cheerful except when he thinks of Susy. S.L.C.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Grant I. Rosenzweig, Kansas City, MO, to Mark Twain with A additions by Mark Twain 1898 March 14, ALS, 3 p.
    Asks him about anti-Semitism in Austria and in events described by Twain in the article, "Stirring times in Austria"; with corrections by Twain in preparation for publication in article "Concerning the Jews."
  - Bainbridge Colby, New York, to Katherine I. Harrison, 1898 March 22; TLS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Re addresses and information she requested.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to [Paul] Lindau, 1898 March 30; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Will send him the books for Her Royal Highness; comments on the bindings of the books; enjoyed correspondent's brother Rudolf's visits very much. M.T.] (mourning stationery)
  - Harper & Brothers, New York, to Henry H. Rogers, New York, 1898 May 18; TLS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Royalty check sent to Olivia L. Clemens for $1861.68 (through December.31, 1897).
  - Mark Twain, Kaltenleutgeben, Switzerland, to Unknown, [1898] May 24; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks correspondent for offer to ship his books; has forgotten artist's address but gives address of the owner of the picture, who permitted the use of the picture for a post card. S.L.C.
  - B. West Clinedinst to Frank E. Bliss, 1898 July 13; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Will send him 2 pictures (oils) which are now nearly dry enough to send.
  - B. West Clinedinst, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, 1898 [July] 29; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Has read Roughing It carefully and finds plenty of subjects for good illustrations; encloses list [not present] of possible subjects; suggests full page drawings for illustrations; comments on "the inquest scene" not humorous but interesting; describes possible illustration of Mark Twain on bucking bronco; offers to meet and discuss ideas; notes his change of address.
  - Alexander and Green, New York, to Henry H. Rogers, New York with 3 PDS, 1898 August 12; ALS, 7 p. (Box 4)
    Cover letter for enclosed three "Satisfaction of Judgement" claims June 4 1895 from New York Supreme Court in Barrow versus Clemens actions for George Barrow, Elizabeth Barrow, and Rebecca Barrow. With three receipts from Elizabeth, George, and Rebecca Barrow, dated 1898 July 9.
  - Mark Twain, Kaltenleutgeben, Switzerland, to Edward W. Bok, 1898 September 2; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Has written several stories in past year, but which are inappropriate for Bok's family magazine; offers him "My Platonic Sweetheart" for a thousand dollars; if he does not want it, requests he mail it to Henry H. Rogers; says he found a misplaced letter he thought he sent explaining why Mrs. Selfridge has misunderstood him. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Edward W. Bok, 1898 October 10; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Has written large part of his Autobiography but only works on it occasionally; feels it is too early to publish it, except as an occasional single chapter and it is inappropriate for a magazine; says editing for a book is different than for a magazine; Olivia edited and approved "My debut as a literary person" and suggested Bok use this article instead of "My platonic sweetheart" but he realized that Bok would need to edit it further and so did not mail it. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Edmund Kloieda, 1898 October 19; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Declines lecture invitation; will only lecture once in the next year; when younger, had no distaste for lecturing, but now finds it difficult. M.T.
  - Brander Matthews, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, Hartford, CT, 1898 November 6; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Acknowledges letter accepting his proposal to write Mark Twain biographical criticism for $300; first paragraph will be ready when he sees Bliss; would like any biographical material available, copyright dates of Twain books, and a set of Twain books published by Bliss; already has the full Harper set.
  - Brander Matthews, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, Hartford, CT, 1898 November 27; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Cover letter for his introduction for Mark Twain's works; asks to see two sets of galley proofs so that a Columbia colleague may also check it; asks for check at Bliss's convenience.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to [Richard Watson Gilder], The Century, [ante 1898 November]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Fragment. Says heading should be "From the London Times of 1904", which he thought of after mailing manuscript. S.L.C.] (mourning paper)
  - Brander Matthews, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, Hartford, CT, 1898 December 2; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Acknowledges receipt of proofs of his Mark Twain article and check; discussion of best position for his introduction in the books.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to James L. Tuohey, England, 1898 December 7; APCS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    "No, that isn't any matter." S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Kaltenleutgeben, Switzerland, to [Rudolf] Lindau, [1898] December 14; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Gives train schedule and proposed itinerary for his visit. S.L.C.] (mourning paper)
  - B. West Clinedinst to Frank E. Bliss, 1898 December 25; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Has been ill with the flu which settled in his eyes and delayed finishing of the drawings (for Mark Twain book); has three drawings nearly finished and will start on the fourth soon.
  - Mollie Stotts Clemens to Samuel E. Moffett and Mary Mantz Moffett, [1898]; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses Mark Twain and Olivia, who hope to be home next year; they received very kindly Dr. Lapsley, who had a letter of recommendation from Mollie Clemens; comments that Twain's poem about Susy was great comfort to her on Orion's death; mentions family news and that she is taking in boarders.] (mourning paper)
  - Mark Twain, to Chatto & Windus, [1898?] June 28; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Twain writes concerning English copyright law
  - [Mark Twain to Frank E. Bliss], [1899 January 1]; ALS (copy), 1 p. (Box 4)
    Praises Brander Matthews ' introductory essay. S.L.C.
  - Mollie Stotts Clemens to Samuel E. Moffett, 1899 [January] 23 "Sunday"; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Came to Mrs. Couche's Thursday and wrote Moffett at home, but has had no reply; hopes no one is ill; at Piermont but does not know how to reach him; hopes all are well and does not want to be any trouble to them.
  - Klaw & Erlanger to Alf Hayman, 1899 February 2; TLS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Suggests Mark Twain's play "Is He Dead?" would fare better if revised by a dramatist.
  - W. G. Smyth, Smyth and Rice, New York, to Alf Hayman, 1899 February 6; TLS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Is returning Mark Twain play manuscript because it is not promising; would like other manuscript when Bill Harris returns it. "In Purgatory" written across letter.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Charles Dudley Warner, 1899 February 15; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Hopes they will be back soon; expresses sorrow at passing of friends; wonders who the new American representative will be and speculates he is not rich; Olivia fairly well and managing business end of their affairs. M.T.
  - Alf Hayman, New York, to C. C. Rice, 1899 February 17; TLS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Comments on three plays by Mark Twain; not able to place "Bartel Turaser"; "In Purgatory" is in hands of William Harris who promises a decision soon; "Is he dead?" best of three; reluctant to return plays yet, may be able to place them. Refers to 1899 February. 2 Klaw & Erlanger to Alf Hayman.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Francis H. Skrine, 1899 March 9; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    If they were going to stay in London, he would gladly accept Skrine's offer; will refer anyone looking for a house to Skrine; likes the hotel they are staying in. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John M. Hay, 1899 March 11; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Requests he not mention Twain's scheme for a postal check. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery)
  - William Lyon Phelps, New Haven, CT, to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 March 26; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Asks for circular on the new uniform edition of Mark Twain works; will be lecturing on Twain at Yale and would like to comment on this edition; his college class reads Adventures of Tom Sawyer in May.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Frank E. Bliss, [1899 March 31]; ANS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Olivia wants Samuel E. Moffett of the New York Journal to write Twain biographical sketch from "these notes" and would like to check it before printing. S.L.C.
  - Brander Matthews, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 April 6; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Has signed half of Mark Twain sheets and will ship by Adams Express, the other half to be sent next week.
  - Brander Matthews to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 April 14; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Is sending the rest of signed Mark Twain prefaces.
  - Thure M. Thulstrup, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, Hartford, CT, 1899 April 17; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Unhappy that his bill not yet paid, but Bliss may remove signed proofs from his studio all the same.
  - Mark Twain to [Percy] Spalding, [1899 May 3]; ANS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    The papers "duly executed" are enclosed. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery calling card)
  - William Lyon Phelps, New Haven, CT, to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 May 9; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Explains he ordered Adventures of Tom Sawyer for his class but the Yale Co-op bought copies from a jobber elsewhere.
  - Mark Twain, Vienna, to Percy Spalding, 1899 May 10; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks him for telegram; leaving for London to place daughter with Madam Marchesi for singing lessons; has said he is going to London for own business so that present teacher will not know until new engagement complete; asks for help in finding hotel in London and asks about Morley's Hotel in particular; details desired accommodations. S.L.C.
  - Frank E. Bliss to Samuel E. Moffett, 1899 May 11; TL, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Dictated. Enclosing sketch (not present) Mark Twain wants Moffett to rewrite; is not sure where he'll put it in the new edition; requests he do it at the earliest convenience.
  - Mark Twain to Percy Spalding, 1899 May 24; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses London hotel reservations Spalding is getting for Clemens family; mentions he had asked Emperor for an audience; discusses travel plans and accommodation needs. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, Broadstairs, England, to Chatto & Windus, 1899 June 4; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Announces temporary change of address; has been unable to find Mrs. Spaulding's address; is staying at Broadstairs on orders from Clara's doctor; keeps quarters at the Prince of Wales Hotel; requests they not make addresses public (AN on env). S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, England, to [Alice Learned] Bunner, New London, CT, 1899 June 6; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Has longtime commitment for a Tragedy of Pudd'nhead Wilson maxim calendar; would not object if she uses another work for a calendar; does not think that Harper & Brothers or American Publishing Company would object; likes the silhouette and would not mind her using it; eager to return to America before next winter's snow begins. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, London, to "Dear Madam" with AN in unknown hand, 1899 June 11; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Unable to attend meeting on 29th because of previous engagement; sympathizes with the cause. S.L.C. With AN at top in other hand: "From Mark Twain on W.S. meeting."
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, 1899 June 21; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Promises to look in on correspondent before leaving town. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain, London, to Douglas Sladen, [1899 July 7]; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks "authors" for honor they have offered him; regrets he will be leaving shortly and will not be in London for awhile so he cannot take advantage of it. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Frank E. Bliss, Hartford, CT, to Samuel E. Moffett, 1899 July 24; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Glad Mark Twain pleased with sketch; had not set it in type yet because he was waiting for Twain's approval; requests he make a change in the copy to see if the correction is better than the original.
  - Mark Twain, London, to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 October 1; ALS, 3 p. (Box 4)
    Has arrived in London and may stay until spring so that Jean can continue treatment; will complete application for copyright; Olivia acknowledges receipt of check; inquires what Harper & Brothers has to do with his English editors; let him know if Harper & Brothers does not object to Bliss using the "Jew article" ("Concerning the Jews") and will not stop him from adding a volume of short works to uniform edition; would prefer to give volume to McClure, which is really Harper & Brothers; suggests Bliss, if he needs to, go through McClure to get a concession from Harpers; expects no trouble though from Harper & Brothers. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, London, to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1899 October 4; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Declines invitation to the Savage Club because he plans to keep out of newspapers for six months; would like to visit him and his family at home; says he is ready to start writing. Signed S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, London, to [Percy Spalding ?], 1899 October 16; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Praises book on Major Noah; has not read beyond answer to North American Review; hopes to use facts furnished by correspondent; says he knew Major Noah's eldest son in San Francisco; gives London address as Chatto & Windus. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, London, to Unknown, 1899 October 19; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Understands now; had been deceived by Smythe's line; cannot lecture and does not expect to be on lecture platform again since he dislikes it. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to Tatlock, [1899 ca. October]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Glad to hear news of Mrs. Tatlock's health; is house hunting. S.L.C.
  - Brander Matthews, New York, to Frank E. Bliss, 1899 November 7; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Had the set of Mark Twain works here all the time but thought they were the sheets; thinks the page on [Life On] The Mississippi a bit crowded but feels it doesn't matter; will sign sheets this week.
  - Olivia L. Clemens, London, to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1899 November [17]; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Thanks him for another book; still is comforted by In Memoriam; enjoyed visit with him; says Twain cannot remember the publishing story MacAlister referred to.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1899 November 24; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses whether Lord Leighton used the Kellgren massage system; asks for confirmation. M.T.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1899 December 1; APCS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Declines dinner invitation since many journalists would be present. S.L.C.
  - Olivia L. Clemens to Mrs. John Young Walker MacAlister, 1899 [ca. December 25]; AN, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Christmas and New Year's wishes to the MacAlisters.] (w/env) (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to Adela Goodrich-Freer, 1900 January 11; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Answers her question on his books.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mary Stotts Clemens to Frank E. Bliss, 1900 January 30; ANS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Suggests canvassing in Ashland, Kentucky, would result in many sales in individual books and uniform sets of Mark Twain works.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 7; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Speculation that Bovril might be the best customer for Plasmon. S.L.C.] (w/mourning env)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 8; ALS, 5 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses his investment in Plasmon and Plasmon matters; would like a theater box; has declined an invitation from the Liberal Club; wants to have the publisher do the proof-reading; suggests title The Man That Corrupted Hadleyburg and Other Stories and Sketches for new book; admits he was fooled by the "Greek" origin of The Celebrated Jumping Frog of Calaveras County story. M.T.] (w/mourning env)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 9; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses the way Bovril is obtained and his estimates of the cost to the company; thinks Bovril syndicate is not making a profit; adds Tatlock coming from Berlin in a week.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain, London, to Caspar Whitney, [1900] March 9; ALS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Unable to write for Whitney because his writing is now committed for the next year or two. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 10; ALS, 2 p. (Box 4)
    Asks him to send Heimberg to Lord George Hamilton's closest friend with suggestion of Plasmon for relieving famine in India at lower bulk and cost than millet. S.L.C.] (w/env)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 17; ALS, 4 p. (Box 4)
    Discusses editing his two volume book and securing the British copyright; mentions Harper & Brothers sending him prints of illustrations for the book. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 23; APCS, 1 p. (Box 4)
    Has not heard from Tatlock but if Butlers' offer is accepted he will help. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 March 24; ALS, 2 p. (Box 5)
    Asks for packages of Plasmon and Virchow's pamphlets for distribution; visited House of Commons. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 April 2; ALS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Will try to bring money to him. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, London, to [C(aspar)] Whitney, 1900 April 20; ALS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Unable to say when he will be free from "mortgage upon my possible work" and so cannot make any promises. S.L.C.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain, London, to Samuel E. Moffett, [1900] April 23; ALS, 3 p. (Box 5)
    Marked private. Says Jean's illness has been diagnosed as epilepsy; has told only two other people, Dr. Helmar and Susan Crane; she is under treatment of Heinrich Kellgren; wishes Moffett to interview Dr. Helmar and sends a list of questions (not present) to ask; wants him to take notes on interview using fictitious names; says Kellgren has promised to cure Jean; depends on Moffet to get all the information he can on and from Helmar. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain, London, to Adela Goodrich-Freer, 1900 May 11; ALS, 2 p. (Box 5)
    Would be delighted to visit her with Olivia, but the girls will be unable to come because of their studies; inquires for convenient date for visit. S.L.C.
  - Vaughan Kester to Henry H. Rogers, New York, 1900 May 15; ALS, 2 p. (Box 5)
    Re two clauses to be added to Adventures of Tom Sawyer dramatization contract; with copy of contract and carbon copy.
  - Olivia L. Clemens to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 June 10; ALS, 4 p. (Box 5)
    Thanks him for box at Prince of Wales Theater; looking forward to seeing Mr. Harvey in the plays there; says Bram Stoker will send them tickets for the Lyceum; reports that Mark Twain has gone to Oxford; best wishes to his wife and ill son.] (mourning stationery)
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 June 11; ALS, 2 p. (Box 5)
    Thanks for the box; reports Olivia has gout and inquires what she should do since she disobeys her doctors. M.T.] (w/mourning env)
  - Olivia L. Clemens to son of John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 June 20; ALS, 2 p. (Box 5)
    Thanks him for tablets sent to her; hopes he is getting better himself; regards to his parents.] (mourning stationery)
  - John Young Walker MacAlister to Mark Twain with AN 1900 June 29 by Mark Twain, 1900 June 28; TLS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Says he is enclosing letter Bram Stoker's letter expressing his opinion on the hypothetical play; since Penley has not submitted his offer, suggests that he go with Cyril Maude. At bottom of letter, AN 1900 June 29 from Mark Twain agrees with MacAlister and returning Bram Stoker's letter to him as requested. M.T.
  - Mark Twain to Unknown, [ca. 1900 June 28 -October 6]; ALS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Knows nothing about Dow machine; advises him to get full information before investing; accepts dinner invitation.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 [July 1]; APCS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Declines invitation; says family moving and he has a prior engagement. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 July 5; APCS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Sends regrets. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 August 1; APCS, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Re his health. S.L.C.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 August 17; APC, 1 p. (Box 5)
    Unable to visit because he had to call on widow of someone who had died suddenly.
  - Mark Twain to John Young Walker MacAlister, 1900 August 18; ALS, 1 p. (Box 5)